♪Wind♪
♪바람이 설레는 정담을 살포시 놓고 가요♪
♪Whispers of love♪
♪정담은 한 사람만 꺾을 수 있기에 아름답죠♪
♪The prosperous life♪
♪번화는 우리가 함께 보낸 사계절이에요♪
♪For the rest of my life♪
♪여생은 달빛을 보며 사랑을 속삭이고 싶어요♪
♪I'll remain elegant for you all my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 아름답고 싶어요♪
♪Giving you my love little by little♪
♪조금씩 사랑을 내려놓고♪
♪I care for you with every piece of my heart♪
♪한결같이 걱정하며♪
♪And I miss you every day and night♪
♪평생 그리워하죠♪
♪I'll be loyal to you in the best years of my life♪
♪그대를 위해 평생 노력할게요♪
♪Melting love with gentle smiles♪
♪웃음으로 사랑을 녹여요♪
♪I won't be afraid of anything♪
♪비바람이 불어도 두렵지 않아요♪
♪And I won't change my heart for you♪
♪해마다 거두는 찻잎처럼 말이죠♪
=Episode 5=
=제5화=
Wen Yu,
문우
if... if you hate this,
혹시 원한이 있는 거라면
go find those men who killed you.
너를 죽인 사람을 찾아가
Whatever you want,
필요한 게 있다면
I'll burn it for you.
내가 전부 태워줄게
I'll burn... I'll burn some paper money.
정말이야, 돈도 다 태워줄게
Or anything. Anything you want.
전부 다 태워줄게
And these pretty women...
그리고 여기 이 미녀들 중에
Pick one.
아무나 한 명 골라
I'll burn anyone you want.
네가 좋아하는 여인으로 태워줄게
These women are boring.
그런 미녀들이 무슨 소용이야
I want you!
나는 너 하나만 원해
Who killed you owes you.
당사자는 내버려두고
Why did you want me?
왜 나를 잡아가려는 거야
You said you didn't want to lose me.
나랑 헤어지기 아쉽다고 했잖아
Why are you scared?
왜 이제 와서 무서워하는 거지?
(He has a shadow. He isn't a ghost.)
(그림자가 있어 귀신이 아닌 건가?)
He feels warm.
따뜻하잖아?
♪Wind♪
♪바람이 설레는 정담을 살포시 놓고 가요♪
His heart beats.
심장이 뛰고 있어
He breathes.
숨도 쉬고 있잖아?
♪The prosperous life♪
♪번화는 우리가 함께 보낸 사계절이에요♪
You aren't dead.
죽은 게 아니야
This is great.
정말 다행이다
Surprised?
놀랐어?
Then who left me there to die?
그때 누가 날 버리고 갔더라?
♪For the rest of my life♪
♪여생은 달빛을 보며 사랑을 속삭이고 싶어요♪
I'm so glad that you're still alive.
죽지 않아서 정말 다행이야
(I didn't know she really feared I would be dead.)
(진짜 내가 죽을까 봐 걱정한 거야?)
♪Giving you my love little by little♪
♪조금씩 사랑을 내려놓고♪
I'm all right.
난 괜찮아
But when will you stop hugging me?
언제까지 안고 있을 거야
Your jade pendant.
옥패는?
It's all right, too.
옥패도 괜찮잖아
This is great.
정말 너무 잘됐어
Are you only worried about the pendant?
옥패만 걱정한 건 아니지?
♪Melting love with gentle smiles♪
♪웃음으로 사랑을 녹여요♪
Not really.
당연히 아니지
When I see you safe and sound,
네가 이렇게 무사하니
I'm really happy.
정말 너무 기쁘다
According to the North Prince,
왕야가 말하길
you died after the failed treatment.
네 부상이 심해 죽었다는 거야
I was worried for a long time.
그래서 얼마나 걱정했는데
I was stabbed and I was dying.
칼에 맞아 죽을 뻔한 나를
But His Highness paid a lot of money for a famous doctor
북왕께서 거금을 써 명의를 불러
who saved my life.
살려주셨어
Can he really be so helpful?
그리 마음씨 좋은 사람이라고?
You said, "The North Prince is righteous
저번에 네가 북왕은 인품이 고귀하고
and handsome.
영민하고 비범한데다
Everybody likes him.
천하의 사랑을 받는 사람이라고 했잖아
You want to see him
그런 북왕을 사모하고
and you adore him."
또 흠모한다면서
But now, you suspect of his kindness?
왜 갑자기 그분의 호의를 의심하는 건데?
I used that trick
그건 내가 네 소식을 찾는다고
just to get some information about you.
생각해 낸 묘책이였던 거지
The North Prince is lecherous.
그 사람이 얼마나 방탕한데
How could he be a nice guy?
좋은 사람일 리 있겠어
What you see is what he appears to be like.
네가 본 건 다 표면적인 것들이야
You haven't really known him.
너는 아직 북왕이 어떤 사람인지 몰라
The North Prince
북왕, 그 사람은
is not only lecherous,
호색한에다가
but also treasonous.
반역을 꾀하고 있다고
Treasonous?
반역?
It records the evidence of his sins.
여기 그 증거가 적혀 있지
Where did you get this account book?
이 장부는 어디서 가져왔어?
Did anyone else see it?
또 누구 본 사람 있어?
Mr. Zhang, who works for the North Prince,
북왕 측근의 서기인 장 대인이
traded this book in the House of Romance
풍월각에서 이 장부를 갖고 거래할 때
and I stole it.
슬쩍 가져왔지
This is my amulet.
이건 내 부적이야
How come it's your amulet?
이게 왜 네 부적이야?
If the North Prince wants to hurt me
나중에 북왕과 혼인했는데
after he marries me,
혹시라도 나한테 무슨 짓 하면
showing this account book
바로 이 장부를 들이밀 거야
will allow me to leave safely.
그럼 완전히 벗어날 수 있겠지
Sounds feasible, Yueling.
괜찮은 방법이네
But this account book may get you killed.
그렇지만 이 장부가 널 위험에 빠트릴 수도 있어
I'm afraid this mansion is no longer safe.
이곳 공주부도 더는 안전하지 않고
Why is it no longer safe?
무슨 소리야?
I guess someone is watching over you.
누군가 이미 널 감시하고 있을지도 몰라
You think you can
너는 이 장부가
so easily keep this account book?
그렇게 쉽게 네 손 안에 들어왔을 거로 생각해?
What... What do I do?
그럼 어떡하지
Do you have any idea?
무슨 방법이 있을까?
You go to the North Prince's mansion.
북왕부로 가
Go there?
북왕부로 가라고?
When you're there,
북왕부에 도착하면
the North Prince will protect you.
북왕이 온 힘을 다해 너를 지킬 거야
You keep this account book, after all.
어쨌든 장부는 네가 갖고 있으니까
Besides, if you're in trouble,
그리고 또 어떤 일이 생기더라도
we can struggle together.
우리가 함께라면 죽을 일은 없잖아
It makes sense.
일리가 있네
(Pleasant and Harmonious)
(혜풍화창)
Your Highness,
왕야
you insisted on going out in the middle of the night.
어쩌자고 야밤에 뛰쳐나가셨어요
Your wound isn't deep.
상처가 깊지는 않아도
But you still need to recuperate.
안정을 취하셔야 한다니까요
You lost the account book.
그깟 장부 하나도 못 간수하고
With you guys around,
일을 이렇게 하면
how can I possibly recuperate?
내 상처가 어떻게 좋아지겠어
Sorry, Your Highness.
죄송합니다, 왕야
We didn't expect her to steal
장 대인에게 일부러 흘린 장부를
the account book we deliberately gave Mr. Zhang.
공주가 가져갈 줄은 생각도 못 했어요
Your Highness,
왕야
will it affect our plan?
설마 이 일로 계획에 차질이 생기진 않겠죠?
If the plan fails, we can think of another one.
계획이야 다시 세우면 되지
So, you asked her to move in ahead of time
그럼 공주님을 보호하려고
just to protect her?
미리 북왕부로 들리신 거예요?
I can't stop worrying
그 남매는
until she and her brother
아무래도 내 옆에 두어야
live around me.
좀 안심이 돼
Looks like we have to go to the North Prince's mansion.
북왕부에 안 갈 수가 없겠는걸
We don't know about that prince.
북왕이 사람인지 귀신인지도 모르겠어요
What if he offends you,
혹시라도 공주님을 희롱하면
Your Grace?
어떡하죠?
If he dares to offend my sister,
만약에 북왕이 그랬다간
I'll kill him immediately.
내가 가만있지 않을 거에요
With this,
이 물건만 있다면
(Account Book) I don't think he dares to offend me.
(장부) 함부로 굴지는 못 할 거야
If the North Prince rebels,
북왕이 반란을 일으켜서
his consort
죄를 묻기 시작한다면
will also be held accountable.
북왕비도 함께 연루될 텐데
Your Grace, will you really marry him?
정말 왕비가 되시려고요?
If I don't marry him,
내가 왕비를 안 하면
Beishuo will break our alliance
북삭은 동맹을 깨고
and destroy our state.
동유를 짓밟을 텐데
By then, none of our people
그럼 우리 동유인들은
can live a good life.
고통 속에서 살아갈 거야
What's worse,
게다가
my eldest sister will be caught.
큰언니도 잡혀오게 될 수도 있어
Then you'll be the sinner
그럼 우리 누님이 완전
of Dongyu.
동유의 죄인이 되는 거잖아요
So will you, Your Highness.
그건 왕자님도 마찬가지잖아요
Don't worry.
걱정 마
With this,
이 물건만 있다면
he won't dare to hurt us.
감히 우리를 어떻게 하지는 못할 거야
If he dares to offend you,
만약 누님에게 예를 갖추지 않는다면
we'll hand over the account book
이 장부를 근거로
and report him to the Emperor of Beishuo.
북삭 황제에게 북왕을 고발해요
That's right.
그래
So,
그렇다면
we'll have to go there.
북왕부는 꼭 가야겠네요
(Account Book) Let's just go.
가면 가는 거지, 뭐
(The North Prince's Mansion)
(북왕부)
Such a big mansion.
엄청 크다
The North Prince is rich.
북왕이 대단하긴 하네요
The yard is carefully cleaned.
정원도 꽤 잘 가꾸었어요
If he's a better man,
인품만 좀 괜찮았어도
I'll allow Yueling to marry him.
우리 누님을 순순히 보내줬을 텐데
Your Highness,
왕자님
you said something different last night.
어젯밤과 말씀이 다르잖아요
I did?
그런가?
You're always chatty.
하여간 나불거리긴
(Benign and Benevolent)
(제월광풍)
Yueling, this room is so big.
누님, 여기 정말 크네요
Your Grace, what's wrong?
공주님, 왜 그러세요?
This room looks beautiful.
이 방 정말 예쁜데요?
I'm just a little bit homesick.
그냥 집이 조금 그리워서 그래
Your Grace, if you want to leave,
공주님께서 가고 싶으시다면
I'll always be with you.
천천이 어디든 함께할게요
Yueling, I hear
누님, 듣자하니
the North Prince lives in the western yard
북왕은 서원에 살고
and he gives you the whole eastern yard.
동원은 전부 누님에게 줬다고 하던데
So, he doesn't want you to see him.
아마 누님이랑 마주치지 않으려는 것 같아요
He doesn't want to see me?
나랑 마주치기 싫다고?
I don't want to see him, either.
그건 나도 마찬가지인걸
Let's just take whatever comes.
기왕 온 김에 편하게 있자고
Since we're given such a good place,
이렇게 좋은 방을 주었으니
let's just enjoy it.
우리 마음껏 즐기자
(Memorial to the Throne) In this case,
아무쪼록
I'll leave the mining thing
철광 채굴과 관련된 일은
to the two of you.
두 분께서 수고해 주십시오
Rest assured, Your Highness.
왕야께선 안심하십시오
Your Highness.
왕야
What?
어때?
Is everything ready for my consort?
왕비의 거처는 꼼꼼히 준비했어?
Don't worry, Your Highness.
걱정 마세요, 왕야
Princess Yueling has settled down in the eastern yard.
월령 공주는 이미 동원에 머물고 계십니다
They're satisfied with their place.
거처에 대해서는 매우 흡족해하고 계세요
Your effort for her isn't wasted.
왕야의 성의가 헛되지 않았어요
Good.
다행이네
Give her two cooks who can make Dongyu dishes.
동유 음식을 할 줄 아는 요리사를 붙여줘
She love those dishes.
공주가 좋아하니까
Yes.
네
Anything else?
또 무슨 일 있어?
I just think
저는 그저 느끼기에
Your Highness cares really a lot
왕야께서 월령 공주님에게
about Princess Yueling.
신경을 많이 쓰는 것 같아서요
Thanks to you
네 덕분에
who lost my account book of illegal mining.
몰래 개발한 철광과 관련된 장부를 잃어버렸으니까
Your Highness,
왕야
Princess Yueling thinks highly of Wen Yu.
월령 공주가 문우에게 호감이 있는 것 같은데
So, you want to trick her of it
그래서 왕야께서는 문우의 신분을 이용해
with Wen Yu's identity, huh?
공주를 속여 장부를 다시 가져오시려는 거죠?
Oh, not trick her.
아, 속이는 게 아니라
You will
그게...
just get it from her.
받아내려는 거죠
My maid Yueling
제게 아월이라고 하는 시녀가 있습니다
received a lot of help from Wen Yu on her way here.
북삭으로 오는 동안 문우의 보살핌을 많이 받아
So, she adores him.
문우에게 호감을 갖게 되었습니다
Yesterday, she accidentally heard
어제 그 시녀가 우연히 듣기를
Wen Yu was assassinated in the House of Romance
문우가 풍월각에서 암살당했다고 하여
and she was really worried.
매우 걱정하고 있어요
I'm so glad that you're still alive.
죽지 않아서 정말 다행이야
You sound so anxious.
공주께서 이렇게 급하신 걸 보면
I think you actually adore him
아월 낭자가 그에게 호감이 있는 게 아니라
instead of Miss Yueling.
공주께서 호감이 있는 것 같습니다
Your Grace,
공주님, 공주님
Butler Wen is here.
문 집사가 왔어요
Why did he come so early?
왜 이렇게 일찍 왔대
Greetings, Your Highness.
왕비님을 뵙습니다
Your Highness ordered me
왕야께서 왕비님을 극진히 모시라고
to take good care of you
특별히 당부하셨습니다
and offer you all the best things.
뭐가 되었든 다 최고로 준비하라 하셔서
So, I picked the four of them
저희가 이들을 특별히 엄선하여
to serve you.
왕비님을 모시도록 하였습니다
Come and meet Her Highness.
왕비님께 얼른 인사드리거라
Greetings, Your Highness. I'm Rubing.
여빙, 왕비님을 뵙습니다
I'm good at makeup and hairstyles.
저는 화장과 머리를 잘합니다
Greetings, Your Highness. I'm Rushuang.
여상, 왕비님을 뵙습니다
I'm good at cleaning.
저는 정리정돈을 잘합니다
Greetings, Your Highness. I'm Dali.
저는 대력이라고 합니다 왕비님께 인사드립니다
I'm good at making Beishuo and Dongyu dishes.
저는 북삭과 동유의 각종 음식을 잘 만듭니다
Greetings, Your Highness. I'm Daqi.
저는 대기라고 합니다 왕비님께 인사드립니다
I'm good at making Beishuo and Dongyu pastry.
저는 북삭과 동유의 각종 다과를 잘 만듭니다
(What is the North Prince up to?)
(북왕은 무슨 꿍꿍이인 거야)
Your Highness, His Highness said
왕비님, 어떠한 분부든
you could ask for anything you wanted.
편히 내리라고 왕야께서 당부하셨습니다
From this day on, the four of them will work for you.
앞으로 이 네 명은 왕비님의 사람입니다
It's really nice of His Highness.
왕야께서 많이 신경쓰셨네요
His Highness also said
그리고 또 왕야께서
(Indenture) you can keep half of their indentures.
노비 계약의 절반을 드리라 하셨습니다
Use them without worry.
사람들을 마음껏 부리십시오
It's quite thoughtful of him.
왕야께서 아주 신경을 많이 쓰셨네
Thank you, Butler Wen.
문 집사님, 고생하셨어요
Your Highness, since they're here,
그럼 하인들을 인계해드렸으니
I'll take my leave.
저는 이만 물러가 보겠습니다
In this case,
지금부터
with Rubing, Rushuang,
여빙, 여상
Dali, and Daqi
대력, 대기
joining us,
너희들이 함께하니
we've grown bigger.
우리가 머무는 이곳이 더 풍성해지겠구나
Oh,
맞다
how about we have a welcome dinner
우리 오늘 저녁에는
of Dongyu style right tonight?
동유만의 특별한 환영 만찬을 열어보는 거 어때?
Why not?
좋죠
Really?
정말요?
Don't be shy.
모두 그렇게 어색할 필요 없어
We're a family now.
우리는 형제자매나 마찬가지야
There aren't too many rules in our state.
우리 동유는 그런 규율 같은 거 없어
You two look so strong.
너희 둘, 정말 든든하네
Hurry.
서두르거라
Bring that thing here.
저것도 가져와
- All right. - And that one.
- 네 - 그리고 저것도
Rubing and Rushuang,
여빙, 여상
hurry up.
서둘러
Come on. Hurry.
빨리, 빨리
The food is done.
나갑니다
- It'll smell great with some spice. - All right.
여기에 향료를 조금 더 넣으면 맛있을 거야
This dish is done, too.
이것도 끝났습니다
Daqi, I want some super spice food.
대기, 나는 엄청 매운 걸 먹고 싶어
Wait a minute. You'll have it.
잠시만요 준비 다 됐습니다
Daqi, give me some.
대기, 나도 두 개만 줘요
You'll all have some.
네, 양은 충분해요
Daqi, give me one.
대기, 나도 한 개만 줘요
Come on, just one.
나 먼저 하나만 줘요
It's for Her Highness. You'll all have some later.
왕비님께 먼저 가져다드리고 여러분께도 드리겠습니다
Slow down.
조심히 잡아
- It's for all of you. - Got it.
알겠어요
- All right. - Wait a minute.
그래
- Give it to me. - Here.
자, 나한테 주라고
Come on. All of you can have some.
다들 여기로 오세요
Yueling, taste it.
누님, 한번 맛보세요
It looks delicious.
보기만 해도 맛있네
I'll take it there.
내가 가져갈게
Put it over there.
저쪽에 놓으면 돼
All right.
알겠습니다
Your Highness.
왕야
Nie Chen,
섭신
do you smell something?
무슨 냄새가 나지 않아?
(Nie Chen, the North Prince’s dark guard) Smells like the roast meat.
(섭신 북왕의 호위무사) 고기 굽는 냄새 같습니다
Your Highness.
왕야
Bad news, Your Highness.
왕야, 큰일 났습니다
What?
무슨 일이냐?
Her Grace is hold a big dinner in her yard.
공주께서 연회를 열었는데
The smell goes everywhere.
그 냄새가 온 마당에 퍼져서
The ladies all went there to see the roast meat.
미인들이 공주께서 고기 굽는 걸 구경한다고
Everything is in a mess.
엉망진창이 됐어요
- In a mess? - Her Grace is roasting meat?
엉망진창?
Am I hearing this right?
내가 잘못 들은 거 아니지?
Yes, Your Highness.
제대로 들으셨습니다, 왕야
We've never seen it before.
백문이 불여일견이라고
Your Highness, go take a look.
얼른 가서 직접 한번 보시죠
Everybody, come on.
모두 오세요
Let's drink together.
같이 마셔요
Come on.
오세요
All right.
좋아요
Wen Yu.
문우
Your Highness.
왕야
Your Highness?
왕야?
Nonsense.
왕야라니
This is Wen Yu, my good buddy.
여기는 내 벗 문우야
There you are, at last.
드디어 왔구나
Let's go have a drink.
자, 술 마시러 가자
Xingyi, Wen Yu is my good buddy.
성습, 문우는 내 좋은 벗이야
- Fill his cup. - Here.
얼른 술을 따라줘
Cheers.
건배
Fill his cup.
가득 채워라
Good buddy,
친구야
we'll help each other and never leave each other.
우리 죽어도 같이 죽고 살아도 같이 살자
Cheers.
건배
You're drunk.
취하셨습니다
Am I drunk?
나 취했어?
I don't know.
모르겠는데요
- No. - You're not.
아니요, 안 취하셨습니다
Her Grace won't be drunk.
우리 공주님께서는 취하지 않으셨습니다
See?
봐봐
I told you.
내가 말했지
I never get drunk.
난 들이부어도 안 취한다고
Why do I see three copies of you?
네가 왜 세 명으로 보이지
One.
하나
Two.
둘
Three.
셋
What is happening to Her Highness?
왕비님, 괜찮으세요?
Come on. Let's drink.
어서 마시자
Wen Yu, it's so nice of you.
문우, 넌 참 좋은 사람이야
♪Clouds slowly float across the sky♪
♪저 멀리 유유히 흐르는 구름♪
♪Telling what is awfully bothering♪
♪헤어지기 아쉽다 말하네♪
♪Ceaseless, love lingers and lingers♪
♪잘라낼 수 없는 그리움에 사로잡혀♪
♪You and I both know it♪
♪사랑하니까 말하지 않아도 알아♪
♪In this world, we stay side by side♪
♪속세에 비할 만큼♪
♪Watching the stars rise and fall♪
♪수많은 별똥별이 깜빡여♪
♪My eyes are red from missing you♪
♪붉어진 두 눈 그리움은 고치가 되고♪
♪Tonight, I hope the moonlight will♪
♪오늘 밤 밝은 달이 네 미간에 떨어지길 바라네♪
♪Promising it'll last forever♪
♪하늘에 맹세했더니♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪오동나무 꽃이 떨어지며 소원을 이뤄주고♪
♪I'll stay with you for thousands of years♪
♪그대와 만 년을 살고 싶어♪
♪Until we grow old together♪
♪백발에 하얀 눈이 내리는 꿈을 꿨네♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪산들바람이 오동나무 꽃을 스치며♪
♪When I look back, you whisper♪
♪그대를 나지막하게 불러♪
♪Then I wake up from the dream♪
♪꿈에서 깨어나 보니 여전히 첫 만남과 같네♪
You're awake?
일어났어?
We...
우리
What is going on here?
어떻게 된 거야?
His Highness married you to me.
왕야가 우리를 혼인시켜주셨어
We've been married for three days.
혼인한 지 벌써 사흘째인데
Why are you still not used to it?
아직도 적응이 안 돼?
We... We're married?
우리가 혼인을 했다고?
You told His Highness you adored me.
왕야께 나를 연모한다 말해놓고는
Why do you not remember?
벌써 다 까먹은 거야?
Be careful, honey.
조심해
Your Grace, time to get up.
공주님, 일어나실 시간이에요
Your Grace.
공주님
Luckily, it was just a dream.
꿈이라니 다행이다
Why would I dream about Wen Yu?
내가 왜 문우 꿈을 꾼 거지
Your Grace, who did you dream about?
누구 꿈을 꾸셨다고요?
Get up and get changed.
얼른 일어나서 치장하세요
Nobody.
아무것도 아니야
Qianqian,
천천
last night,
나 어젯밤에
how did I come back to my room?
방에 어떻게 돌아온 거야?
Your Grace, I was also drunk last night.
어젯밤에는 저도 취해서요
When I woke up, you were asleep in the room.
일어나 보니 공주님께서는 이미 방에서 주무시고 계셨어요
Besides,
그리고
you can drink more than I do.
공주님 주량이 저보다 더 세잖아요
But...
근데...
Did I come back by myself?
내 발로 돌아온 건가?
Wen Yu,
문우
it's so nice of you.
넌 정말 좋은 사람이야
I flirted with Wen Yu.
내가 문우에게 질척거렸다니
No wonder I had that kind of dream.
그러니 그런 꿈을 꿨지
Your Grace, did you have a nightmare?
공주님, 악몽을 꾸신 거예요?
Never mind. A dream is always opposite.
걱정 마세요 꿈은 반대라잖아요
Indeed, a dream is always opposite.
그럼 그렇지
Your Highness, Her Highness has moved in.
(혜풍화창) 왕비님이 북왕부에 계신데
Will you still visit the House of Pretties?
미인각에 가시려고요?
Isn't it inappropriate?
그건 조금 곤란하지 않을까요?
Now, Yueling lives here.
아월이 북왕부에 들어왔으니
It may be dangerous to keep those ladies.
궁녀들을 이렇게 두는 게 위험할 수도 있어
I should go meet them.
한번 둘러보러 가는 것이다
You're right.
그것도 그렇네요
I think Her Highness will understand.
왕비님께서도 분명 이해하실 겁니다
There you go.
얼른 가봐
Yes.
네
Your Grace, you...
군주, 여긴 어찌...
I'm moving back.
(고락이 북삭의 군주) 다시 돌아왔으니
(Gao Luoyi, Commandery Princess of Beishuo) I'm going to greet my cousin.
사촌 오라버니께 인사드리러 가는 길이네
Welcome back, Your Grace.
다시 돌아오신 걸 환영합니다
But you had a long trip.
(미인각) 긴 여정으로 지치셨을 텐데
How about you get back for some rest?
일단 쉬시지 않고서요
Where is my cousin?
오라버니는 어디 계신가?
His Highness is in the middle of something.
왕야께서는 지금 바쁘십니다
Is he in the House of Pretties?
혹시 미인각에 계시는 건가?
I'm here with an imperial decree.
나는 지금 궁의 명을 받들어 이 자리에 왔다
I must see him now.
지금 당장 오라버니를 만나야 해
- But... - Do you want him to disobey the decree?
하오나...
But...
아닙니다
Hey, Your Grace.
군주님, 군주님
Shiyu.
오라버니
- Your Highness. - Shiyu.
- 왕야 - 오라버니
You cheap woman.
이 천한 계집애가
How dare you sit on my cousin's laps?
감히 우리 오라버니 다리에 앉다니
Get out of here.
얼른 썩 꺼지지 못해?
Luoyi, what are you doing?
락이, 이게 무슨 짓이냐?
When I was away from this house,
내가 북왕부를 비우는 동안
women like you
너희들이
became cubbish, huh?
규율을 다 잊어버린 모양이다
Your Highness, that's not true.
왕야, 억울합니다
- We aren't. - Your Highness, we aren't cubbish.
아닙니다, 그렇지 않습니다
- Your Highness. - Yeah.
왕야
Shiyu, I hate it when they seduce you.
오라버니
You... Get out of here!
얼른 꺼지지 못해?
All right. Leave us.
됐다, 모두 물러가거라
Humph.
참나
Aren't you supposed to accompany the Great Consort in the palace?
너는 궁에서 태자비를 모셔야 하지 않아?
What are you doing here?
왜 여기에 온 거야?
Knowing you're going to marry someone,
오라버니가 새 신부를 맞는다길래
I'm here to greet her.
락이도 새언니께 안부를 여쭈러 왔지요
And...
그리고
You won't be living here again, will you?
또 여기 눌러앉으려는 건 아니겠지?
I will, of course.
그야 당연하죠
I'm here under the command of the Great Consort.
저는 명령을 받들러 왔습니다
You must not kick me out.
함부로 못 내쫓는다고요
I hear
듣자하니
Her Highness and her servants got drunk last night.
왕비께서 어제 하인들과 함께 술에 취하셨다고 하시던데
The scandal even made its way to the palace.
이 일이 벌써 궁에도 전해졌습니다
I'm here to give her a present.
저는 왕비님께 선물을 드리러 온 거예요
Present?
선물?
Where is Xingyi?
성습은 어디에 간 거지?
His Highness has gone to the House of Romance
왕자님께서는 풍월각에 가신 것 같아요
for the assassin, I think.
무슨 여살수를 찾는다고 하시던데요
Your Highness,
왕비님
this is the western yard.
이쪽이 서원으로
It's where His Highness lives.
북왕 전하의 침전입니다
You can't get in without permission.
하여 통행이 불가한 점을 미처 아뢰지 못했군요
Why?
왜 안 된다는 건가?
Our princess
저희 공주님께서는
will be the North Princess Consort.
북삭의 북왕비이신걸요
Why can't she walk around?
그런데도 안 된다는 건가요?
You must not break in.
이곳은 마음대로 들어가실 수 없습니다
Who are you?
누구시죠?
Her Highness is the North Princess Consort.
저희 공주님께서는 북왕비십니다
Just because of this,
왕비님이시기 때문에
I have to stop you.
소신이 막아서는 것입니다
Your Highness, this is Madam Dong from the palace.
왕비님, 이분은 궁에서 오신 동유모입니다
She was assigned by the Great Consort
태자비께서 특별히 동유모를 보내시어
to teach you Beishuo etiquette.
왕비님께 북삭의 예절을 교육하도록 하셨습니다
What? Teach me etiquette?
예절 교육이요?
What etiquette?
어떤 예절이요?
(The House of Romance)
(풍월각)
See you.
조심히 가세요
Gentleman, come in, please.
공자님, 안으로 드시지요
Who do you...?
실례지만 어쩐 일로 오신 건지요?
Have Miss Su Nian come out and see me.
소염 아가씨를 불러주게
I'm sorry.
정말 죄송합니다
Miss Su Nian has a day off.
소염 아가씨는 오늘 쉬는 날이랍니다
How about some other girls?
아니면 다른 아가씨는 어떠세요?
Su Nian is having a day off.
소염이 오늘 쉬는 날이지만
But if you insist on seeing her,
공자님께서 꼭 보시고자 한다면
you can see her.
당연히 만나 봬야죠
Su Nian.
소염
You must give this guest
귀한 분이 오셨으니
a great time today.
오늘 정말 잘 모셔야 한다
Get it?
알겠느냐?
Yes.
네
Still laughing?
여전히 웃고 있네
It's not when
말에서 나를
you dumped me off the horse, huh?
밀어버릴 때처럼 말이야 그렇지?
You're so good at acting.
연기를 정말 잘하네
I don't know what you're talking about.
소염은 도통 무슨 말씀인지 모르겠습니다
You'll know soon.
조금 있으면 알게 될 거다
Gentleman, what would you like for today,
오늘은 노래를 들으러 오셨나요?
a song or a dance?
아니면 춤을 보시겠어요?
Martial contest.
나와 대결해
Assassin, we're here alone.
여살수, 오늘은 우리 둘뿐이다
Stop acting. Bring it on!
연기는 그만하고 덤벼
It's so humorous of you.
정말 재밌으십니다
But I can only dance
소녀는 가무만 할 줄 알지
instead of doing martial arts.
무술은 할 줄 모르옵니다
What?
뭐 하는 거냐?
Gentleman, what do you think of this dance?
이 춤이 마음에 드시나요?
No...
아니
Not that good.
별로다
(Do I really get the wrong girl?)
(내가 정말 잘못 본 건가)
(Looks like she isn't)
(아무래도 저자는)
(the assassin.)
(여살수가 아닌가 보네)
Stop.
멈추세요
One more time.
다시 한번 걸어보세요
Stand properly.
서 있는 자태도 신경쓰셔야죠
You should behave elegantly.
모든 동작은 우아해야 합니다
Put your hands before you.
손을 앞에 두세요
Relax your shoulders and stay straight-backed.
어깨 힘을 풀고 허리를 펴세요
Head up.
머리를 드세요
This is the way I've been standing for a dozen years.
십여 년간 이렇게 서 있어 왔지만
I don't think anything is wrong with it.
아무런 문제가 없었네
Because you Dongyu people are impolite.
그건 동유인들이 예의를 모르고
You have no manners.
규율이 없기 때문입니다
Can politeness be food
예의가 밥을 먹여주지도 않고
or be clothes?
옷을 입혀주지도 않는데
I think I'll just stop learning this.
내가 봤을 땐 배우지 않아도 아무 상관이 없네
You...
이 무슨 태도입니까
I used to teach the imperial consorts only.
수많은 후궁들을 가르쳐 왔지만
No one dared to reject my instruction.
여태껏 제 교육을 거부한 사람은 없었습니다
Your Highness, stand straight up.
왕비님, 얼른 일어나십시오
Because you didn't meet me before.
그건 그전에 나를 만난 적이 없었기 때문이지
I'm not an obedient Beishuo girl.
나는 결코 온순한 북삭 여인이 아니라고
- That's right. - You...
옳소
So, this is the rumored Eldest Princess of Dongyu?
이분께서 바로 대단하신 동유의 공주님이시군요
I hear my cousin-in-law is the most virtuous lady in Dongyu
듣자하니 새언니께서는 동유에서 가장 정숙하시며
and she is really elegant.
어질고 고운 마음씨를 지닌 여인이라고 하던데
What? You can't even walk properly?
근데 설마 걷는 것도 못하시는 건 아니시겠죠?
Who are you?
그쪽은 또 누구십니까?
Princess Luoyi is the sister of Lord of the South
저희 락이 군주께서는 남왕의 친동생이시자
and the cousin of the North Prince he favors most.
북왕께서 가장 아끼시는 사촌 동생이십니다
Did Her Highness even talk to you?
우리 공주님께선 너한테 물어본 거 아니거든?
Why did you interrupt?
왜 끼어들고 있어
Qianqian, fall back.
천천, 가만히 있어
They have no manners,
저들이 예의범절이 없다고
but we need some.
우리도 똑같이 할 수는 없지
Princess Luoyi, you sound so sarcastic.
락이 군주께서 이렇게 괴팍하신 걸 보니
You seem to impolite, too.
가정교육이 그렇게 대단하진 않은 것 같네요
- I... - Well, I'm generous enough.
아니...
How about Madam Dong gives you some lessons?
유모를 양보할 테니 수업을 듣는 게 어떻겠습니까?
You... You're impolite
가정교육을 못 받은 건 그쪽이죠
and you have no manners.
예의범절도 없고 말이에요
You disgraced my cousin that much
우리 북왕 오라버니 체면을 그렇게 깎아먹고서는
and even the imperial family heard about it.
그 소식이 이미 궁에도 퍼졌다고요
However poorly I behave,
내가 아무리 부족하더라도
I am your cousin-in-law.
윗사람인데
You're in no position to judge me.
아랫사람에게 가르침을 받을 순 없는 노릇이죠
I should show
아니면 내가 군주의 말버릇을
your caring cousin
배워서, 그 뭐냐
how sarcastic you are
군주를 가장 아끼는 북왕께 보여드려야겠습니다
and see what he'll comment.
뭐라 말씀하시는지 한번 보고 싶네요
- You... - Good point, Your Highness.
이게...
- Good. - I dare you!
옳습니다
Let's wait and see.
어디 한번 두고 봐요
See if I dare.
내가 과연 그렇게 못 할지
- Qianqian. - Here.
- 천천 - 네
See them out.
배웅해 드려라
Yes.
알겠습니다
(Huilan Pavilion) To be the North Princess Consort,
(회란정)
I have to learn so many things.
이것도 배워라 저것도 배워라
Why are there so many rules in Beishuo?
북삭에는 뭐 이렇게 규율이 많은 거야
How I miss my hometown.
집이 정말 그리워
What's on your mind?
무슨 생각해?
You freaked me out.
깜짝이야
What are you doing here?
여긴 왜 왔어?
I heard you were learning etiquette lately.
요즘 무슨 규율 같은 거 배우고 있다며
How do you feel?
어때?
I don't think I'm fit for this state.
나는 북삭이랑 안 맞아
Why?
왜?
Madam Dong used to serve the Empress.
동유모는 황후를 모시는 자라
You can learn a lot from her.
많은 걸 배울 수 있을 텐데
It's really hard to learn your local manners.
너희 북삭의 규율은 너무 어려워
I love my state.
나는 여전히 우리 동유가 좋아
We live a free and equal life there.
거긴 자유롭고 평등하거든
You're homesick?
집이 그리운 거야?
The ladies we dispatched to the North Prince's mansion
저희가 북왕부에 심어둔 여인이
have been expelled.
쫓겨났습니다
Another calligraphy is ruined.
또 좋은 글귀 하나를 망쳤구나
What a loser!
이 쓸모없는 자식
The North Prince's mansion is more heavily guarded.
북왕부에서 경계를 강화하고 있습니다
Our men
저희 쪽 사람이
can no longer sneak in.
더 이상 들어가기 어려운 상황입니다
You can't even sneak
그 작은 북왕부 하나도
into a mere prince's mansion.
못 들어가?
Don't be angry, Prime Minister.
부디 화를 거두십시오
I've arranged everything.
소인이 이미 계획해 두었습니다
It's all under deployment.
모든 것이 준비됐습니다
Looks like
주시여
Zhou Shiyu won't hide anymore.
숨기 싫은 모양이구나
Who's there?
누구냐
Lingxi?
영석
(Lingxi, the assassin of the Roufeng Sect) Su Nian, you still remember me.
(영석 유풍문의 살수) 언니, 저를 기억하시는군요
It's been years.
몇 년 만인데
You look more gorgeous, Su Nian.
소염 언니는 날이 갈수록 아름다워지네요
No wonder rich young guys in the Capital City
어쩐지 상경성의 공자왕손들이
spent money like water just to see you.
언니 얼굴 한번 보려고 돈을 그렇게 쓰더라니
How have you been these years?
요 몇 년간 어떻게 지냈니?
I've been doing dirty missions.
암담한 임무만 수행하고 있어요
I naturally don't live a great life
언니가 누리는
as you do in the House of Romance.
풍월각의 안락함보다 못 해요
I have to flatter people here.
풍월각에서 아첨하며 살아가는 생활도
My life isn't that great.
편하다고 말하기는 어려워
Master sent me here
제가 찾아온 건 주인님의 명을 받들어
to assist you in your new mission.
언니와 협력해 새로운 임무를 완수하기 위해서예요
Assist me?
협력?
Master is angry because you failed last time.
지난번 임무에 실패해 주인님께서 화나시긴 했지만
But he's giving you a second chance.
언니에게 기회를 한번 더 주시기로 하셨어요
(It's her.)
(그자야)
She came here before
이자가 일전에 풍월각에서
and stole the account book Master wanted.
주인님이 찾고 계시는 장부를 가져갔어요
Our mission
우리의 이번 임무는
is to find her and get the book back.
이자를 찾아 장부를 가져오는 거예요
I'm grateful for Master's not discarding me.
주인님의 뜻을 받들어
I'll complete this mission.
사명을 다하겠어
Rushuang, let me help you.
여상, 내가 도와줄게
Your Grace, it's weird.
공주님
Madam Dong used to come very early.
원래 유모는 아침 일찍부터 찾아왔는데
But now, it's late in the morning.
지금 해가 중천에 떴는데도
She still hasn't come.
아직도 안 오고 있어요
I wish she would never come again.
다시는 안 왔으면 좋겠는데 말이지
Her manners
그 규율 때문에
are nearly crushing me.
괴로워 죽겠어
Your Grace, why is Mr. Lin here?
공주님 임 대인이 왜 왔을까요?
Greetings, Your Highness.
왕비님께 인사드립니다
Why is it you?
왜 임 대인이 오신 거죠?
Why can't it be me?
제가 오면 안 되나요?
Your Highness,
왕비님
His Highness sent me here for a message.
왕야께서 특별히 저를 통해 말씀을 전하게 하셨습니다
Since you've learned a lot,
왕비님께서 충분히 많이 배우셨기에
Madam Dong has returned to the palace.
동유모는 궁으로 돌아가게 하셨습니다
Does it mean
그 뜻는
I no longer need to learn anything?
이제 예절 공부는 끝났다는 말인가?
That's right, Your Highness.
맞습니다, 왕비님
Why?
왜 갑자기?
His Highness gave the order.
왕야께서 친히 내리신 명입니다
I guess he cares for you, Your Highness.
아마 왕비님을 아끼는 마음에 그러하신 것 같아
I can't ask too much about the other stuff.
소인도 더 이상 여쭈어 보진 않았습니다
All right. I get it.
그래, 알았네
I'll take my leave, then.
그럼 소인은 물러가 보겠습니다
I no longer need to learn anything!
이제 안 배워도 된다
♪Clouds slowly float across the sky♪
♪저 멀리 유유히 흐르는 구름♪
♪Telling what is awfully bothering♪
♪헤어지기 아쉽다 말하네♪
♪Ceaseless, love lingers and lingers♪
♪잘라낼 수 없는 그리움에 사로잡혀♪
♪You and I both know it♪
♪사랑하니까 말하지 않아도 알아♪
♪In this world, we stay side by side♪
♪속세에 비할 만큼♪
♪Watching the stars rise and fall♪
♪수많은 별똥별이 깜빡여♪
♪My eyes are red from missing you♪
♪붉어진 두 눈 그리움은 고치가 되고♪
♪Tonight, I hope the moonlight will♪
♪오늘 밤 밝은 달이 네 미간에 떨어지길 바라네♪
♪I'll always be in love with you♪
♪그대와 영원히 함께하고 싶다고♪
♪Promising it'll last forever♪
♪하늘에 맹세했더니♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪오동나무 꽃이 떨어지며 소원을 이뤄주고♪
♪To have joy for the rest of its life♪
♪남은 생은 웃음꽃만 피우리♪
♪I'll stay with you for thousands of years♪
♪그대와 만 년을 살고 싶어♪
♪Until we grow old together♪
♪백발에 하얀 눈이 내리는 꿈을 꿨네♪
♪As the breeze blows, the flower fades♪
♪산들바람이 오동나무 꽃을 스치며♪
♪When I look back, you whisper♪
♪그대를 나지막하게 불러♪
♪Then I wake up from the dream♪
♪꿈에서 깨어나 보니 여전히 첫 만남과 같네♪